let set9=
[
    {
        question:`1. Which of the following is the correct sequence of food chain?`,
        options:
        [
            'A. Grass → insects → frog → snake → eagle',
'B. Eagle → snake → frog → insects → grass',
'C. Grass → snake → frog → insects → eagle',
'D. Insects → grass → frog → eagle → snake',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: A`,
        exp:`
        Explanation: All animals, whether herbivores or carnivores, depend
        ultimately on plants for food. Organisms which feed on plants often
        get eaten by other organisms, and so on. For example, grass is eaten
        by insects, which in turn, is taken by the frog. The frog is consumed
        by snakes. This is said to form a food chain: Grass → insects →
        frog → snake → eagle. Many food chains can be found in the
        forest. All food chains are linked. If any one food chain is disturbed,
        it affects other food chains too.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`2. In the context of decomposition, which of the following assertions is/are correct?
        1. Decomposers feed upon the dead plant and animal tissues and convert them into a dark coloured substance called humus.
        2. These are helpful in maintaining the supply of nutrients for plants and animals.
        Use the code given below to choose the correct answer.
        `,
        options:
        [
            'A. 1 only',
'B. 2 only',
'C. Both 1 and 2',
'D. Neither 1 nor 2',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: C`,
        exp:`
        Explanation: The micro-organisms which convert the dead plants and
        animals to humus are known as decomposers. These microorganisms
        play an important role in the forest. The presence of humus ensures
        that the nutrients of the dead plants and animals are released into
        the soil. From there, these nutrients are again absorbed by the
        roots of the living plants and the dead animals become food for
        vultures, crows, jackals and insects.” In this way, the nutrients are
        cycled. So, nothing goes waste in a forest.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`3. Select the chain that contains primary consumers:`,
        options:
        [
            'A. Bird, rabbit, elephant',
'B. Grass, parrot, snake',
'C. Snake, hawk, tiger',
'D. Bacteria, fungi, viruses',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: A`,
        exp:`
        Explanation: A primary consumer is an organism that feeds
        on primary producers. Organisms of this type make up the
        second trophic level and are consumed or predated by secondary
        consumers, tertiary consumers or apex predators. Primary
        consumers are usually herbivores that feed on autotrophic plants,
        which produce their own food through photosynthesis. Several other
        feeding strategies are also used by primary consumers: algivores
        feed on photosynthetic algae; frugivores feed on the fruiting bodies
        of plants; nectarivores feed on plant nectar; folivores feed
        on leaf material; granivores feed on grains and seeds while
        fungivores feed on heterotrophic fungi such as mushrooms. Many
        primary consumers adopt several different feeding strategies in
        order to maximize the effectiveness of foraging behavior.
        Primary consumers often have specific physiological adaptions that
        allow them to process the carbohydrates produced through
        photosynthesis, which can be hard to break down and extract
        nutrition from; herbivores often have rows of wide, flat teeth are
        used to rasp, grind and tear tough plant material and woody stems.
        Many primary consumers also have symbiotic bacteria, which live
        within a special organ called the cecum and assist with the digestion
        of plant material.
        Primary consumers exist in all biomes and fill a wide variety
        of niches. They can range from microscopic organisms such
        as zooplankton to animals as big as elephants.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`4. The correct arrangement in the order from upper layers to lower layer in forests is:`,
        options:
        [
            'A. Trees, Shrubs, herbs, vegetation.',
'B. Vegetation, herbs, shrubs, trees.',
'C. Trees, herbs, shrubs, vegetation.',
'D. Vegetation, shrubs, herbs, trees.',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: A`,
        exp:``
    },
    {
        question:`5. Consider the following statements regarding adaptation in plants and animals.
        1. The presence of specific features or certain habits, which enable
        a plant or an animal to live in its surroundings, is called adaptation.
        2. A person who lives in the plains, breathes rapidly in a hilly region,
        but becomes normal after a few days. This is an example of
        adaptation.
        Which of the statements given above is/are correct?
        `,
        options:
        [
            'A. 1 only',
'B. 2 only',
'C. Both 1 and 2',
'D. Neither 1 nor 2',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: A`,
        exp:`
        Explanation: Adaptation does not occur over a short period of time.
        It is related to the plants and animals adapting themselves to the
        changes having occurred over millions of years.
        If we live in the plains and suddenly go to high mountain regions, we
        may experience difficulty in breathing and doing physical exercise
        for some days. We need to breathe faster when we are on high
        mountains. After some days, our body adjusts to the changed
        conditions on the high mountain. Such small changes that take place
        in the body of a single organism over short periods, to overcome
        small problems due to changes in the surroundings, are called
        acclimatisation.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`6. Through which of the following parts does cactus
        photosynthesise?
        `,
        options:
        [
            'A. Leaves',
'B. Stem',
'C. Roots',
'D. It does not photosynthesise',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: B`,
        exp:`
        Explanation: Cactus is a desert plant. Desert plants lose very little
        water through transpiration. The leaves in desert plants are either
        absent, very small, or they are present in the shape of spines. This
        helps in reducing loss of water from the leaves through
        transpiration.The leaf-like structure you see in a cactus is, in fact,
        photosynthesis in these plants is usually carried out by the stems.
        The stem is also covered with a thick waxy layer, which helps to
        retain water.Most desert plants have roots that go very deep into
        the soil for absorbing water.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`7. In India the area under forest cover is about of the total
        area?
        `,
        options:
        [
            'A. 10%',
'B. 11%',
'C. 20%',
'D. 21.67%',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: D`,
        exp:`
        Explanation: The total forest cover (TFC) of India is 712,249
        square kilometres (sq km) according to the biennial State of India’s
        forest Report 2019 (SoFR 2019) released on December 30, 2019.
        India has set a target of bringing 33 per cent of its geographical
        area under forest cover. The TFC of India in 2019 is 21.67 per cent
        of the total geographical area (TGA) of the country as against 21.54
        per cent (of TGA) in 2017. In 2011, the TFC in India was 6,92,027
        sq km. Hence, even though the TFC increased by 20,222 sq km
        or three per cent since 2011, there are some concerns over the
        growth pattern of our forests this decade.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`8. Column-I Column-II
        A. Crown 1. Branches of tall trees forming a roof in a forest
        B. Understory 2. Plants that climb another trees
        C. canopy 3. different horizontal layers in forests
        D. Creepers 4. Branchy part of tree above the stem
        `,
        options:
        [
            'A. 3 2 1 4',
'B. 4 3 1 2',
'C. 2 1 4 3',
'D. 1 4 3 2',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: B`,
        exp:``
    },
    {
        question:`9. Consider the following:
        1. Growth
        2. Response to stimuli
        3. Reproduction
        Which of the above is/are symptoms of living things (plants and
        animals)?
        `,
        options:
        [
            'A. 1 and 2 only',
'B. 1 and 3 only',
'C. 2 and 3 only',
'D. 1, 2 and 3',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: D`,
        exp:`
        Explanation: Changes occuring in the environment are called stimuli,
        like pricking of a thorn, bright light, etc. All the living things show
        response towards stimulus. Leaves of touch me not (Mimosa) plants
        fold/shrink when touched. This is an example of response to
        stimulus. Reproduction occurs in both, plants and animals, but the
        methods are different.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`10. Plants take in air during respiration. What does the plants
        do in the next step?
        `,
        options:
        [
            'A. Utilise carbon dioxide and give out oxygen into the atmosphere.',
'B. Utilise oxygen and give out carbon dioxide.',
'C. Utilise both carbon dioxide and oxygen',
'D. Give out both oxygen and carbon dioxide.',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: B`,
        exp:`
        Explanation: While respiration, the exchange of gases in plants
        occur through the leaves. Plants take in the air through the stomata
        and utilise the oxygen. They release carbon dioxide into the
        atmosphere. During photosynthesis, plants use carbon dioxide in the
        presence of sunlight to make their own food and release oxygen.
        Plants make their food only during the day; while they respire during
        the day and night both. Oxygen released during photosynthesis is
        much more than that used during respiration.
        `
    }
]